{"tossups": [{"question": "In the nineteenth century, this country experienced the Liberal Triennium. An attempt to enforce the Salic Law in this country sparked the first Carlist War. This country lost nearly all of its overseas colonies during the early nineteenth century following the rise of Jose de San Martin and Miguel Hidalgo. For 10 points, name this onetime master of much of Latin America.", "answer": "<b><u>Spain</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The major theoretical advance of these people was recalculating the Smeaton coefficient to correct errors made by Otto Lilienthal. These rivals of Samuel Langley worked as publishers of <em>The West Side News</em> and as bicycle salesmen before their breakthrough at Kill Devil Hills. For 10 points, identify this pair of Ohio brothers who made the first airplane flight in 1903.", "answer": "<b><u>Wright</u></b> Brothers [Wilbur and Orville <b><u>Wright</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "During this battle, Strong Vincent was killed at a site where the downhill bayonet charge led by Joshua Chamberlain occurred. This battle, which included the skirmish of Little Round Top, turned on an ill-advised \"charge\" ordered by Confederate general George Pickett. For 10 points, name this July 1863 clash in Pennsylvania which was the turning point of the Civil War.", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Gettysburg</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This field of research was what John McCarthy was working on when he invented the LISP programming language in 1959. This field of research is the subject of John Searle's \"Chinese Room\" argument and is divided into \"weak\" and \"strong\" branches. For 10 points, name this field which seeks to duplicate functions of the human brain on computers.", "answer": "<b><u>artificial intelligence</u></b> [or <b><u>AI</u></b>, prompt on \u201ccomputers\u201d or \u201ccomputer science\u201d]", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "A 2006 contest resulted in two of these animals being given the politically explosive name \"reunion.\" In August 2014, one of these animals was given a first birthday party by the U.S. National Zoo, and another one of these animals, Ai Hin, was caught faking a pregnancy to earn more bamboo. For 10 points, name these endangered Chinese bears.", "answer": "giant <b><u>panda</u></b>s", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "This man once sold cards displaying Lon Horiuchi's home address at gun shows. This man was inspired by reading about a fictional race war in <em>The Turner Diaries</em> and by the incident at the Branch Davidian compound in Waco. For 10 points, name this conspirator, with Terry Nichols, who was executed for his role in the 1995 bombing of the Murrah building in Oklahoma City.", "answer": "Timothy <b><u>McVeigh</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Karl Jaspers (<b>pr. YOS-perz</b>) is often called a Christian philosopher within this framework. This philosophy was dubbed \"a humanism\" in a book by one of its major exponents, who also wrote <em>Roads to Freedom</em>. For 10 points, identify this philosophy originated by Soren Kierkegaard and popularized by Jean-Paul Sartre (<b>pr. SART</b>) in which humans must create meaning in the universe.", "answer": "<b><u>existential</u></b>ism", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "This actor played a Mexican revolutionary in <em>Viva Zapata!</em> and <em>Mark Antony</em> in the 1953 Julius Caesar. He utters the last words \"the horror\u2026the horror\" in his role as Kurtz in <em>Apocalypse Now</em>. This star of<em> The Wild One</em> sent American Indian activist Sacheen Littlefeather to accept his Oscar for another role. For 10 points, name this portrayer of Vito Corleone in <em>The</em> <em>Godfather</em>.", "answer": "Marlon <b><u>Brando</u></b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "A song of this kind derives its melody from \"La Montovana,\" the same folk song that is the origin of \"The Moldau\" (<b>pr. MOLE-dow</b>), and is called \"Hatikvah\" (<b>pr. hah-TEEK-vuh</b>). Songs of the kind include Jana Gana Mana (<b>pr. jah-NAH guh-nuh MOO-nuh</b>) and La Marseillaise (<b>pr. MAHR-see-YEZ</b>). For 10 points, identify this type of song, such as \"God Save the Queen.\"", "answer": "<b><u>national anthem</u></b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Misc Arts"}, {"question": "This man's visit to the Keeling Islands inspired his book <em>The Structure and Distribution of</em> <em>Coral Reefs</em>. As part of that same trip with Robert FitzRoy, he noticed that different finches on the Galapagos Islands occupied different niches. For 10 points, name this man whose time on the <em>Beagle</em> inspired him to introduce the theory of evolution by natural selection.", "answer": "Charles <b><u>Darwin</u></b> <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 4 </b> <b>Second Quarter </b>", "metadata": "Science - Biology"}, {"question": "Eddie Collins achieved this stat six times in a game on two separate occasions in September 1912. In 1962, Maury Wills became the first modern player to achieve this feat a hundred times in a season, and Lou Brock once broke Ty Cobb\u2019s record for this statistic. For 10 points, name this baseball achievement whose records are now held by speedster Rickey Henderson.", "answer": "<b><u>stolen base</u></b>s [or <b><u>steal</u></b>s]", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "This man's victory at the 1040 battle of Elgin allowed him to become King of Alba, displacing Duncan I. In a fictionalized portrayal, this man is killed in battle with an opponent who, having been delivered by Caesarean section, fulfills the prophecy that \"no man of woman born\" can kill him. For 10 points, name this King of Scotland killed by Macduff in a Shakespeare play.", "answer": "<b><u>Macbeth</u></b>", "metadata": "Literature - British Literature - Drama"}, {}, {"question": "This man's co-conspirators included Mary Surratt, who became the first woman executed by the U.S. government as a result, and the doctor Samuel Mudd. This man's brother Edwin once saved Robert Lincoln from being crushed by a train. This man interrupted a performance of <em>Our</em> <em>American Cousin</em> to shout \"Sic semper tyrannis!\" For 10 points, name this disgruntled Confederate actor who assassinated Abraham Lincoln.", "answer": "John Wilkes <b><u>Booth</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "The U.S. National Archives currently displays David Rubenstein\u2019s copy of this document, which contains clauses that limited the right of women to use the legal system and limited the enforcement of debts against children. This document was signed at Runnymede and failed to quell the Barons Wars. For 10 points, name this limitation of the powers of King John.", "answer": "<b><u>Magna Carta</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This empire was targeted by the Unilateral Declaration of Independence, which removed a colony from this empire to protest its plans for racial integration. This empire's leader gave the Winds of Change speech as it began to give up control of Ghana, Nigeria, and Rhodesia. For 10 points, name this empire which, along with France, was the largest colonizer of Africa.", "answer": "<b><u>British</u></b> Empire [or the <b><u>UK</u></b>; or the <b><u>U</u></b>nited <b><u>K</u></b>ingdom; or Great <b><u>Britain</u></b>; prompt on <b><u>England</u></b>]", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "This man's lavish spending on Italian art greatly expanded the Royal Collection. This man is depicted with a stable boy, a horse, a walking stick, and red trousers, looking away from the Thames (<b>pr. TEMZ</b>), in a portrait of him \"at the hunt.\" For 10 points, name this king whom Anthony van Dyck repeatedly painted prior to his execution in the English Civil War.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles I</u></b> of England [prompt on <b><u>Charles</u></b>]", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "This empire was attacked by Croesus (<b>pr. CREE-sus</b>) of Lydia after the Delphic Oracle said that \"a great empire will fall.\" This empire relied on local satraps who were loyal to emperors sitting at Susa. For 10 points, name this empire founded by Cyrus the Great, which launched a namesake series of wars on Greece at the start of the fifth century BC.", "answer": "<b><u>Persia</u></b>n Empire [or <b><u>Achaemenid</u></b> Empire]", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was giving a speech that contained the line \"Caesar had his Brutus, Charles the First his Cromwell\" when he was interrupted with shouts of \"Treason!\" Later, this advocate of resisting the Stamp Act said \"I know not what course others may take.\" For 10 points, name this Virginia orator who ended that speech with \"give me liberty or give me death.\"", "answer": "Patrick <b><u>Henry</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b><u>Theodor Adorno said that after the existence of this place, writing poetry is barbaric.</u></b> <b><u>This place was built near a massive, forty-four track (+)</u> railway junction and was commanded by Rudolph Hoss. At the main gate of this place, the words \"Arbeit Macht Frei\" (</b>pr.ARR-bite mokt FRY<b>), meaning (*)</b> \"work makes free,\" were spelled out in iron. It was adjacent to the Birkenau extermination center. For 10 points, name this most active Nazi death camp, found in Poland.", "answer": "<b><u>Auschwitz</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b><u>These people were the target of 1913's Alien Land Law. These people were guaranteed</u></b> <b><u>equal access to public schools as part of the (+)</u> \"Gentlemen's Agreement\" which restricted their further immigration. They were later relocated to facilities such as Manzanar as part of a practice upheld by the (*)</b> Supreme Court in the <em>Korematsu</em> case. For 10 points, name this group which was subject to World War II \"internment\" on the West Coast.", "answer": "<b><u>Japanese</u></b>-Americans", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the third century AD, this building was the home of a red idol with a golden right</u></b> <b><u>hand that depicted Hubal. The construction of this building was traditionally attributed to</u></b> <b><u>(+)</u> Ibrahim, who journeyed with his son Ishmael to a spot near the Well of Zamzam. This building was cleared of idols near the start of the (*)</b> Islamic era and is now the destination of the hajj, or pilgrimage. For 10 points, name this black, square building around which Mecca is built.", "answer": "the <b><u>Kaaba</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "<b><u>A U.S. State Department memo on this initiative said that it was \"a flying saucer\u2014</u><u>nobody knows what it looks like, how big it is, in what direction it is moving, or whether it</u></b> <b><u>really exists.\" Ultimately, this program transferred (+)</u> seventeen billion dollars in cash and goods, and hardened (*) </b>Cold War divisions as Soviet client states were forbidden to participate. For 10 points, name this 1947 initiative under which American money was pumped into Western European economies.", "answer": "<b><u>Marshall</u></b> Plan", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Other Social Science"}, {"question": "<b><u>This program was upheld as Constitutional by the Supreme Court in the cases of</u></b> <em><b><u>Steward Machine Company v. Davis</u> </b></em><b><u>and</u> </b><em><b><u>Helvering v. Davis</u></b></em><b><u>. This program was inspired by</u></b> <b><u>the \"revolving\" plan advocated by Francis (+)</u> Townsend, and it issued its first card to Ida May Fuller. The first, two billion dollar wave of (*)</b> taxes collected to fund this program may have triggered the 1937 recession. For 10 points, name this retiree pension program in the United States.", "answer": "<b><u>Social Security</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1988, the U.S.S.</u> </b><em><b><u>Vincennes</u> </b></em><b><u>accidentally shot down a passenger plane from this</u></b> <b><u>country. Kermit Roosevelt led a CIA action against the prime minister of this country,</u></b> <b><u>Operation (+)</u> Ajax, which deposed Mohammad Mossadiq. Jimmy Carter's decision to allow the deposed ruler of this country to seek medical treatment in the U.S. in (*) </b> 1979 sparked an incident here. For 10 points, name this country which took fifty-two Americans hostage for over a year.", "answer": "<b><u>Iran</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>An event which began on this ship provided the nickname for Molly Brown. Frederick</u></b> <b><u>Fleet was unable to avert disaster aboard this ship despite performing adequate lookout</u></b> <b><u>duties, and many of its (+)</u> survivors were picked up by the </b><em><b>Carpathia</b></em><b>. Edward J. Smith captained this ship on behalf of the (*)</b> White Star Line. For 10 points, name this ship whose attempt to make good time to New York caused it to hit an iceberg and sink in the north Atlantic in April 1912.", "answer": "<em>RMS</em> <em><b><u>Titanic</u></b></em>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In an 1890 treaty, this empire abandoned its interest in Zanzibar in exchange for an</u></b> <b><u>oddly shaped territory that granted it access to the Zambezi River, known as the Caprivi</u></b> <b><u>Strip. This empire perpetrated the Herero genocide in what is now</u></b> (+) <b>Namibia. It had to give up what are now Tanzania and Cameroon following its defeat in </b>(*) World War I. For 10 points, name this European-based empire, which was originally constructed by Otto von Bismarck.", "answer": "<b><u>German</u></b> Empire  <b>NHBB C 2014-2015 </b> <b>Bowl Round 4 </b> <b>Tiebreakers/extras ONLY USE IF A BACKUP OR TIEBREAK IS NEEDED! </b> This man was able to return to his hometown following negotiations with the tribe of the Quraish (<b>pr. koo-RYE-eesh)</b> at the Treaty of Hudaybiyyah (<b>pr. hoo-dah-BEE-ah</b>). This man was buried next to an empty tomb which is reserved for the returned Jesus after he died in the home of his wife Aisha (<b>pr. eye-EE-shuh</b>). For ten points, name this man who received a \"recitation\" from the angel Jibril (<b>pr. jib-REEL</b>) which became the Quran, and was the founder of Islam.  ANSWER: <b><u>Muhammad</u></b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}